<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Innoq on Stefan Tilkov’s Blog</title>
    <link>https://www.innoq.com/blog/st/categories/innoq/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Innoq on Stefan Tilkov’s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://www.innoq.com/blog/st/categories/innoq/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>innoQ Company Events</title>
      <link>https://www.innoq.com/blog/st/2012/09/innoq-company-events/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Sep 2012 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.innoq.com/blog/st/2012/09/innoq-company-events/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since the beginning of &lt;a href=&#39;http://www.innoq.com/en/&#39;&gt;innoQ&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s existence, 13 years
ago, we&amp;rsquo;ve maintained a regular schedule of so-called &amp;ldquo;company
events&amp;rdquo;. In my opinion, this is one of the really, really great things
about innoQ, and it&amp;rsquo;s also quite different from what others do.
Which is a sufficient excuse for me to write this &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what&amp;rsquo;s an innoQ event? All of innoQ&amp;rsquo;s consultants meet at some more
or less remote venue and spend two or three days there, discussing
projects, technology, methods, in general: anything of interest to our
work. Most of the time we use the classical conference format (an
innoQ person presents something, followed by sometimes controversial
discussion), but we use other approaches, such as open spaces, pecha
kuchas, and lightning talks, too. We occasionally invite guests (we
were lucky to have e.g. &lt;a href=&#39;http://steve.vinoski.net/blog/&#39;&gt;Steve Vinoski&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#39;http://jexp.de/blog/&#39;&gt;Michael Hunger&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#39;http://www.voelter.de&#39;&gt;Markus Voelter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#39;http://www.michaelnygard.com/blog/&#39;&gt;Michael Nygard&lt;/a&gt; pay us a
visit). While the location is mostly somewhere in Germany, we go to
Switzerland sometimes, and one event per year is reserved for a trip
&amp;ldquo;far far away&amp;rdquo; (in the past years we went to e.g. Prague, Barcelona,
Paris, Rome, Budapest, and Strasbourg; these are the only events where
we actually spend a day just sightseeing). Some of the events focus on
project reports, others are programming events, one event per year is
dedicated to company strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is amazing to most people I talk to about this is the frequency we do this
with, and the resulting amount of time, effort and money we invest. We
do 6-8 events per year, 2 of them three days long, the rest two
days. Events are always scheduled during regular workdays,
typically Thursdays and Fridays; attendance is mandatory. This adds up
to 15-18 days per person per year, with the most significant cost
factor being the &amp;ldquo;lost&amp;rdquo; revenue. Of course there&amp;rsquo;s also a lot of effort
involved in organizing the whole thing: The colleague who does this
essentially organizes 6-8 small conferences (we&amp;rsquo;re regularly about 50
people these days) per year (no small feat; thanks, Thomas).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s worth every single cent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Company events are among the very best things about innoQ. They serve
to help us to spend some quality time discussing various topics,
whether it&amp;rsquo;s company strategy, a new programming language, library,
framework or product, a new approach to project management, or some
very project-specific problem. We&amp;rsquo;re also able to invite candidate
employees to a setting where they have a great chance to get to know
how innoQ works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly of all, they&amp;rsquo;re &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt;. We spend a lot of time doing
geek things, but there&amp;rsquo;s always time for great food, occasional
drinks, and socializing and talking about other important things in
life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you see me tweet from Barcelona during the next three days (where I
plan to spend some time with the works of one of my favorite &lt;a
href=&#39;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antoni_Gaud%C3%AD&#39;&gt;artists&lt;/a&gt; tomorrow),
you know why I&amp;rsquo;m there.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>