<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rest Roca on Stefan Tilkov’s Blog</title>
    <link>https://www.innoq.com/blog/st/categories/rest-roca/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rest Roca on Stefan Tilkov’s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://www.innoq.com/blog/st/categories/rest-roca/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Announcing &#34;ROCA&#34;</title>
      <link>https://www.innoq.com/blog/st/2012/03/announcing-roca/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2012 19:46:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.innoq.com/blog/st/2012/03/announcing-roca/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the past few days, we finally managed to write down a few ideas on
Web frontend design, basically a set of rules to apply if the goal is
to come up with a Web app that is actually &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt; the Web as opposed to
be &lt;em&gt;tunnelled through&lt;/em&gt; the Web. We tried to come up with a catchy
name, and finally arrived at &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#39;http://roca-style.org&#39;&gt;ROCA&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, a
conveniently pronouncable acronym for &amp;ldquo;Resource-oriented
client architecture&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am aware that for many folks, specifically those who are interested
in REST and thus likely to read this, a common reaction might be
&amp;ldquo;Duh&amp;rdquo;. And one of the main things I&amp;rsquo;d like to stress is that we have
not invented a single thing, but rather collected a certain set of
rules that we found many people liked, but couldn&amp;rsquo;t name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we started discussing this, we&amp;rsquo;ve found strong support, as well
as violent opposition. Which is exactly what we were looking for,
because in only very very few cases, people didn&amp;rsquo;t understand what we
described, and that&amp;rsquo;s the whole point of the effort: Give a name to a
certain cohesive set of practices so that they may used as a reference
both when you agree with them, want to build a system that adheres to
them or criticize them because you disagree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to comments over at the &lt;a
href=&#39;http://roca-style.org/discussion.html&#39;&gt;discussion page&lt;/a&gt;. If
you believe we should make changes, please &lt;a
href=&#39;https://github.com/innoq/ROCA&#39;&gt;fork the GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt; and
create a pull request.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>